Hello, everybody!
大家好！我是Google Advanced Solutions
Lab的机器学习工程师Benoit Dherin。
My name is Benoit
If you want to know more about what the Advanced Solutions Lab is, please
如果你想了解更多关于Advanced Solutions
Lab的信息，请点击描述框下方的链接。
follow the link below in the description box.
There is lots of excitement currently around generative AI and new advancements,
围绕着生成性AI和相关的新技术取得了令人兴奋的进展，例如像新
的Vertex AI特性如GenAI Studio，Model Garden，GenAI API等。
including new Vertex AI features such as GenAI
Studio, Model Garden, GenAI API.
Our objective in this short session is to give you a solid footing
在这个简短的课程中，我们的目标是帮
助你了解一些生成式AI的基本概念。
on some of the underlying concepts that make all the Gen AI magic possible.
Today, I’ll go over the code that’s complementary
今天，我将讲解与同一系列的“编码器-解
码器架构概述”课程相辅助的代码。
to the “Encoder-Decoder Architecture Overview” course in the same series.
We will see together how to build a poetry generator
我们将一起学习如何从头开始使用编码
器-解码器架构建立一个诗歌生成器，
from scratch using the encoder-decoder architecture.
Using the angular decoder architecture
you’d find to set up instructions in our GitHub repository.
你可以在我们的GitHub Repo找到设置指南。
Okay, let's now have a look at the code.
好的，现在让我们看一下代码。
To access our lab, go in the asl-ml-immersion folder.
要访问我们的Lab，请进入asl-ml-immersion文件夹。
Then the notebooks folder.
然后是notebooks文件夹。
Then the text_models folder.
然后是text_models文件夹。
That's the lab that we'll cover today.
这就是我们今天要讲的实验。
In this lab we will implement a character based text generator
在这个实验中，我们将基于编码器解码器
架构实现一个基于字符的文本生成器。
based on the encoder decoder architecture.
Character based means that the tokens consumed
基于字符意味着网络消耗和生成的Token是字符而不是单词。
and generated by the network are characters and not words.
We will use plays as a data set.
我们将使用剧本作为数据集。
They have a special structure
它们有特殊的结构，就像人们在彼此对话。
And here you see an example of a piece of text
你在这里看到的是一个由训练过的神经网络生成的文本示例，
that has been generated by the trained neural network.
When the sentences are not necessarily making sense
即使这些句子没有必然的意义，
nor are grammatically correct.
也不一定符合语法规则，
This is remarkable in many ways.
但仍然有很多值得注意的地方。
First of all, remember, it's character based.
首先，记住，它是基于字符的。
So it means that it learns to predict only the most probable characters.
所以它只学习预测最可能的字符。
Despite that, it was able to learn pretty well
尽管如此，它还是学得很好
And also the basic structure of a play with the characters talking to each other.
以及剧本的基本结构，角色彼此对话。
of what is a very small network, as you will see, it's based on the rnn
你将看到的这个非常小的网络是基于RNN 0架构的，并且只在
Vertex AIr工作台上训练了30个周期，这是一个非常快的训练时间。
So let's look at the code now.
那么现在我们来看看代码。
So the first thing is to import the libraries that we need.
首先要导入我们需要的库。
In particular, we could or encoder decoder architecture
特别是，我们可以使用TensorFlow Keras来导入编码器解码器架构。
using TensorFlow Keras to impart that.
using tf.keras.utils.get_file.
使用tf.keras.utils.get_file。
So now the dataset is on disk and we just need to load it into a variable called text.
现在数据集已经在磁盘上，我们只需要将其加载到变量text中。
So the text variable now contains the whole string representing
这个text变量现在包含了代表整个莎
士比亚剧本数据集的整个字符串。
all the all the plays in that Shakespeare dataset.
Can I have a quick look at what it is?
我可以快速看看它是什么吗？
You have the first citizens speaking to
有第一位公民对所有人说话，然后所有人对第一位公民说话。
everybody and everybody else is speaking
to the first citizen.
The cell computes the number of unique characters that we have in that
这个单元计算我们在文本数据集中有多少唯一的
字符，我们看到我们有65个唯一的字符，对吧？
in the text dataset, and we see that we have
65 unique characters, right?
These characters would be the tokens that the neural network will consume
这些字符将是神经网络在训练和生成过程中将消耗的Token。
during training and will generating during this service.
now is to vectorize the text.
What do we mean by that?
向量化是什么意思呢？
It means that first of all,
这意味着我们首先需要从实际的字符串序列中提取出字符序列，
we will need to extract
from the actual string sequence of characters, which we can do
我们可以用TensorFlow的tf.strings.unicode_split来做到这一点。
with TensorFlow by using tf.strings.unicode_split.
So now, for example, texts
以现在，例如，文本在这里被转换成了字符序列的列表。
here are transformed into a list
of sequences of characters.
A neural network cannot consume immediately.
神经网络不能直接消耗字符，我们需要将它转换成数字。
The characters.
We need to transform that into numbers.
So we need to simply map each of the characters to a given
所以我们需要简单地将每个字符映射到一个给定的id。
id. For that we have the
为此我们有tf.keras.layers.
StringLookup，你只需要将你的词汇表列表
传给它。
to which you just need to pass to
the list of your vocabulary.
The 65 unique character that we have in our corpus
我们在语料库中有的65个唯一字符，然后我们生
成一个层，当传入字符时，它会产生相应的id。
will produce corresponding ids.
So within that, that layer you have a mapping that has been generated
在那个层中，你有一个已经生成的字符和id之间的映射。
between the characters and the
id. To get the inverse mapping,
要获得反向映射，你使用相同的字符串查找
层，使用从第一层获取的相同的词汇表。
you use the same layer of string lookup
with the exact same vocabulary that you retrieve
from the first of the year by using get vocabulary.
But you set that parameter to be true, invert, equal equal true,
但你将参数设置为真，invert等于True，
and that will compute the invert mapping, which is the mapping from
那将计算反向映射，即从id到字符的映射。
Right.
And indeed, if you pass to this mapping
实际上，如果你传递一系列ID给这个映射，它会给你返回对应的字符，
sequence of ID’s, the ID’s,
it gives you back
the corresponding characters.
Using the mapping that start in the memory of this layer.
使用在这个层的内存中存储的映射。
So that's that.
就是这样。
Okay.
好的。
Now let's that's been the dataset that we will train our neural network with.
现在我们来准备我们将用来训练神经网络的数据集。
For that we are using the
我们使用了tf.data.Dataset API，它有一个
很好的方法叫做“from_tensor_slices”，
tf.data.Dataset API,
from tons of slices
which will convert.
That answer of instance represents or whole corpus of text of plays
它将把一个实例数组，代表我们的整个剧本文
本语料库的id，转化为一个TF data数据集。
as id it will store that into it to have data data sets.
So at this point, the elements of these datasets
此刻，这些数据集的元素仅仅是单个字符。
are just the individual characters.
So that's not great for us.
这对我们来说并不理想。
But we want to feed our neural network with our sequences
我们想要给我们的神经网络提供的是
等长的序列，而不仅仅是一个字符。
of the same length but not just one character.
We need to predict the next character. So
我们需要预测下一个字符。
but luckily the
但幸运的是，
dataset API has this nice function batch that will do exactly that for us.
数据集API有一个很好的功能叫做
“batch”，它能完美地为我们做到这一点。
So if we pass, if we invoke the batch
所以如果我们在我们的ID数据集上调用“batch”方法，
method on our ID dataset,
to which we pass a given sequence length,
并传递一个给定的序列长度（这里我们设定为100），
which we said to be 100 here, now the elements,
are no longer characters, but the sequences of
100 characters.
So here you see an example.
这里有一个例子。
If we take just one element, they are no longer characters,
如果我们只取一个元素，那么它们不再
是字符，而是百位的字符ID序列，
but sequences of hundreds of their character IDs
0 you want not characters, but character IDs.
你需要的不是字符，而是字符ID。
Okay, it's
好的，我们还没完全完成。
not completely we are not completely done here.
We still need to create
我们仍然需要创建我们将传给解码器的
输入序列，以及我们想要预测的序列。
the input sequences that we were going to pass to the decoder
and also the sequences that we want to predict.
Right?
对吧？
And what are the sequences that are just the sequences of the next character
那么，这些序列是什么呢？它们只是输入序列中下一个字符的序列。
in the input sequence?
So for instance, here, if we have the sequence TensorFlow
例如，如果我们有序列TensorFlow
and the sequence TensorFlow at the beginning,
并且在开始时有序列TensorFlow，
then the input sequence we can do from
在序列的开头，我们能从中得到的输入序列
是"Tens-or-flow"（省略了最后一个W），
it is tens-or-flow, We know the W
is the same sequence, but just shifted by one
on the right, so ensor-low and
所以是"ensor-flow"，
you see that E is the next character for Ring T
你可以看到E是T的下一个字符，N是E的下一个字符，等等。
and is the next there for E, etc.
So basically this little function does exactly that.
基本上，这个小函数就是实现这一功能的，
It takes an original sequence, creates
它接受一个原始序列，通过截断这个序列（去掉最后一个字符）创
建一个输入序列，目标序列则是从第一个字符开始创建的。
an input sequence from that by just truncating that sequence
0 removing the last character and that just the target sequence is created
by started at starting add the first character.
So how we do that, we just map
我们怎么做呢？我们只需将这个分割输入目
标函数映射到我们的序列数据集即可。
the split input target function to our sequence dataset.
Okay.
好的。
And it's already does it.
这样就完成了。
Now let's see how to build the model.
现在让我们看看如何构建模型。
First off, we set a number of variables
首先，我们设置一些变量：
the vocabulary size, the size of the vectors.
词汇表大小，我们希望表示字符的向量的大小（我认为应该是256），
We want to represent the characters will I think That would be 256
and a number of neurons or recurrent layer we'd have.
以及我们的循环层的神经元数量。
For the model itself.
对于模型本身。
It's a relatively simple model.
这是一个相对简单的模型。
We create it by using the Keras subclass API.
我们通过使用Keras子类API来创建它。
We create just a new class called MyModel
我们创建了一个新的叫做"MyModel"的
类，并从tf.keras.Model中子类化。
and we subclass here
from tf.keras.Model.
When you do that you only have to
当你这样做的时候，你只需要覆盖两个函数，构造函数和调用函数。
override two functions, the constructor and the call function.
So let's see what each of these function does.
那么让我们看看这两个函数分别做什么。
The first function takes essentially the hyper parameters of your model,
第一个函数主要接收模型的超参数，
the vocabulary size, the embedding dimension, the number of neuron
即词汇表大小，嵌入维度，神经元数量，
that number of neurons for your recurrent layer,
and it just constricts the layers you will need and store them
然后它只是构建你需要的层并将它们存储为类的变量。
as variables of the class.
Okay.
好的。
Now really
而这些层是如何连接的，
how these layers are connected,
all that is specified in the call function,
所有这些都在调用函数中指定，也就是你的网络架构。
the architecture of your network, if you will.
If you want.
如果你想的话。
Let's see where to the body does. Here.
让我们看看这个函数主要做什么。
Take the input which are sequences of ids representing the characters.
它接收输入，也就是代表字符的id序列。
We have a first layer that we'll create for each of the
我们有一个第一层，它会为每一个输入创建一
个代表那个输入的向量，也就是训练层。
inits a vector representing that.
So that's the training layer.
We'll start to be more and more meaningful.
At least that's the idea.
至少这是我们的想法。
Then these static representations of the characters
然后，这些静态的字符表示被传递给循环层，它会根
据之前看到的内容的上下文来修改这些表示，
is passed to the recurrent layer that we'll somehow
modify these for representation
according to the context of what I've seen with what has been seen
并生成一个代表之前看到的内容的状态，这将在下一步被重用。
previously and generate a state of
what is seen previously, that would be a reuse in the next step.
Finally, we pass the output of the
最后，我们将循环层的输出传递给一个密集层，它
将输出与我们的词汇表中的数量相同的数，
as many numbers that we as we have in our vocabulary,
score for each
of the possible 65 characters and the score
represent the probability of the character
being the next one.
So that's all that the model does.
这就是模型做的所有事情。
Then we instantiated.
首先，我们实例化了模型。
Once we have done that, we can look at the structure of the model
有了模型后，我们可以通过使用模型摘要来查看模型的结构。
using model summary, and you see here you have the I'm building the year,
你会看到我们刚刚在模型中实现的嵌入层、循环层和密集层。
the recurrently year and the dust layer that we just encoded
implemented in our, in our model
does that.
就是这样。
So let's train the model.
接下来，我们要训练模型。
Before we train the model, we need a loss and that's the loss function
在训练模型之前，我们需要一个损失函数，
that we compared the output of the model with the truth, right?
我们将用它来比较模型的输出和真实结果。
Since that's essentially a classification problem with many classes
由于我们的问题本质上是一个多类分类问题，
and the classes being
类别就是可能的下一个字符，所以我们会使用损
失函数SparseCategoricalCrossentropy。
each of the possible characters to be the next,
the loss would be the SparseCategoricalCrossentropy loss.
And also because the neural network
由于神经网络的输出（对数）并不直接对应概率，
but from the logits scores.
Okay,
好的，
once we have the loss, we can combine our model,
有了损失函数后，我们可以编译模型，
which means that basically we tied to it a loss and also an optimizer.
也就是为模型附加损失函数和优化器。
And that will update the weights during training
优化器将在训练过程中更新权重，尽可能地减少损失。
to decrease the loss as much as possible.
Basically, it
此外，我们还设置了一个在训练过程中保存权
重的回调函数，这是一个很有用的工具。
then here we have a little bit of a callback that we will use
and that will save the weights during training,
which is a useful
And we are all set up now to start the training.
至此，我们已经准备好开始训练了。
So we do a model.fit on the data set.
我们对数据集执行model.fit，选择想要训练的轮次。
We choose a number of epochs we want to be trained on.
An epoch is a full pass on the data set.
一轮是对数据集的一次完整遍历。
So here we we have a look at ten, ten times
在这里，我们将数据集遍历了十次，
the corpus of plays we have in our text vector
and we give the callback to make sure
并在训练过程中使用回调函数确保权重被保存。
that the weights are saved during the the training,
that's it.
就是这样。
We have a train model now what do we do with it?
现在我们有了训练好的模型，接下来我们该怎么做呢？
And that's a bit of a complication in the
在编码器-解码器架构中，你不能直接使用你的模型，你
需要编写一个解码函数来一步步解码生成的文本。
encoder.
Decoder architecture is that you cannot through the immediately use your model,
you need to write a sort of a decoding function that's here
that will decode the generated text
a step at a time using the trained model.
Okay.
好的。
So here in this case, we chose to
在这个例子中，我们选择将解码函数作为一个Keras模型实现。
implement this decoding function
as a Keras model.
So we subclass from the tf.keras.Model.
我们从tf.keras.Model子类化。
The main method
模型中的主要方法是生成一步。
in that model is to generate one step.
It's a quick look to what it does,
这个方法接收输入，即你希望编码器-解码器模
型完成、预测、生成新字符的初始字符序列。
so it takes the inputs so the input can be
to prompt the initial prompt initial the sequence of character you want to
the encoder-decoder model to
complete, to predict, to generate new new characters.
So you bypass the input it
然后，它将这段文本转换为一串字符，然后再转换为一串id。
transform that text into a sequence of character,
and then the sequence of characters into a sequence of ids.
Using the ids_from_chars.
使用了ids_from_chars方法。
Here we have a setup previously, and then we call our model
这里我们之前有一个设置，然后我们调用我们的模型
or encoder-decoder model that has been previously trained.
或者之前训练过的编码器-解码器模型。
And what does it do?
它做什么呢？
It takes this input of ids and
它会接收id输入并输出预测的对数。
output the predicted logits.
So this calls for the most probable token the most probable character in this case,
这个对数对应了最可能的Token，也就是最可能的字符，
0 along with the state that summarizes what has been seen previously.
以及一个总结前面看到的内容的状态。
From the predicted logits, we can compute, we can select
从预测的对数中，我们可以选择最可能的Token或字符。
the most likely tokens or characters.
But before doing that there is a little bit of a trick,
在做这之前，有一个小技巧，
which is that we divide the logits by a temperature, by a number.
就是我们会将对数除以一个温度(temperature)值。
So basically if the temperature is one, nothing happens.
基本上，如果温度是1，就没有任何变化。
But if the temperature is very high,
如果温度很高，它会使得所有Token的得分变得接近于0，
what it will do, it will makes the scores
associated to each of the token to be predictive.
Next will be relatively similar, close to zero.
This means that actually
这意味着这个Token更有可能被选中。
this token would be more and more likely to be chosen, right?
So there would be more variety, more a more stuff can be predicted
所以，如果温度更高，会有更多的多样性，
if the temperature is higher.
So it's a bit more creative If you have a two high temperature,
更多的内容可以被预测，这会使得模型变得更有创造性。
of course, the neural network would just predict the gibberish.
如果温度太高，神经网络只会预测出无意义的东西。
Okay.
好的。
And if you have a true temperature, the highest probability
如果温度非常低，最高的概率得分会被乘以一个非常大的数，
score will be just multiply by a very large number
because it's divided by a small number, it's a number between zero and one,
因为它被一个小数除，这是一个介于0和1之间的数字，
which means that the highest score will be
这会使得最高得分的Token有更大的被选中的
概率，也就是说，模型的行为会更加确定。
become much, much
bigger than the other scores, giving a much higher chance
to be selected, which gives you more of the deterministic behavior.
Okay, that's the temperature.
好的，这就是温度。
That's an important parameter, as in this type of architecture.
所以，温度是这种架构中一个重要的参数。
Okay.
好的。
And that's what it does.
这就是它的功能。
Okay.
好的。
So now we have the predicted logits we use tf.random.categorical
有了预测的对数后，我们使用tf.random.categorical
从这些概率分数中随机选择下一个最可能的id，
to just sample from these probability scores
the most likely idea is to be next.
We transform that back to a character and that's what we return.
然后将它转换回一个字符，这就是我们返回的结果。
Okay, So that's essentially what the decoding function does
好的，这就是解码函数的主要工作，大多数解码函数都是这样的结构。
There is also this temperature trick that you can see as a
这个设置“温度”参数的技巧，你也可以应用在大语言模型中。
as a parameter in the case of large
language models.
Okay, so let's use our decoding function.
好的，接下来，我们要使用解码函数。
So typically you use that in the loop.
通常，你会在一个循环中使用它。
So here we are going to predict 1000 characters by repeatedly
在这里，我们将通过反复调用解码函数生成1000个字符。
making a call to the decoding function generated one step,
what has been predicted
before, along with the state summarizing what happened before,
and it predict the next character along with a new state.
它会预测下一个字符和一个新的状态，
And we start the process.
然后我们就可以开始这个过程了。
We do sort of a prompt here. That's
我们以“罗密欧（Romeo）”作为Prompt。
Romeo.
What are you going to say? And then the
你打算说什么？然后看看神经网络生成的结果。对吧？
Says no good corona at least take your feetle
生成的是：“no good corona at least take your
feetle and if I seem to my love you...”
and if I seem to my love you...
so you see it's not it doesn't make a lot of sense here.
你会看到，结果并没有完全符合语法规则，
0 Remember I've trained it only a few minutes
这是因为我只在Vertex AI工作台上用很短的时间训练了这个模型。
on the work bench,
AI work bench in Vertex AI Workbench, which are great by the way, but here
that's a small instance which just one GPU So it was a very small training.
这是一个小实例，只用了一个GPU，所以训练规模很小。
The model is written
模型的代码只有几行，
in a few lines, but yet you still see that it can really pick up
但你仍然能看到，它真的能从输入数据的结构中捕获到很多东西。
a lot of things in the structure of the of the input data.
It detects patterns that you have characters.
它能够检测到你输入的字符模式。
but then
然后神经网络生成了“莱昂特斯（Leontes）”，
Leontes was generated by the network and then what
以及“莱昂特斯”说的话。
Leontes says. So
okay,
好的，就这样。
that's it.
If you like this presentation, you'll find more on our ASL
如果你喜欢这个介绍，你可以在我们的ASL
GitHub Repo中找到更多的机器学习Notebooks。
GitHub repository with 90 plus machine learning and notebooks.
Don't forget it.
如果你觉得这个Repo很有用，请给我们的Repo加星星⭐️。
Thanks for your time.
感谢你花时间来听我讲解。